The police response to a community in mourning was to use force to impose fear: fear of militarized police, imprisonment, fines. The media even tried to make us afraid of each other by the way they spun the story. And all of these things have worked in the past. But like I said, this time it was different. Michael Brown's death and the subsequent treatment of the community led to a string of protests in and around Ferguson and St. Louis. When I got out to those protests about the fourth or fifth day, it was not out of courage; it was out of guilt. See, I'm black. I don't know if y'all noticed that. (Laughter) But I couldn't sit in St. Louis, minutes away from Ferguson, and not go see. So I got off my ass to go check it out. When I got out there, I found something surprising. I found anger; there was a lot of that. But what I found more of was love. People with love for themselves. Love for their community. And it was beautiful -- until the police showed up. Then a new emotion was interjected into the conversation: fear. Now, I'm not going to lie; when I saw those armored vehicles, and all that gear and all those guns and all those police I was terrified -- personally. And when I looked around that crowd, I saw a lot of people that had the same thing going on. But I also saw people with something else inside of them. That was courage. See, those people yelled, and they screamed, and they were not about to back down from the police. They were past that point. And then I could feel something in me changing, so I yelled and I screamed, and I noticed that everybody around me was doing the same thing. And there was nothing like that feeling. So I decided I wanted to do something more. I went home, I thought: I'm an artist. I make shit. So I started making things specific to the protest, things that would be weapons in a spiritual war, things that would give people voice and things that would fortify them for the road ahead. I did a project where I took pictures of the hands of protesters and put them up and down the boarded-up buildings and community shops. My goal was to raise awareness and to raise the morale. And I think, for a minute at least, it did just that. Then I thought, I want to uplift the stories of these people I was watching being courageous in the moment. And myself and my friend, and filmmaker and partner Sabaah Folayan did just that with our documentary, "Whose Streets?" I kind of became a conduit for all of this courage that was given to me. And I think that's part of our job as artists. I think we should be conveyors of courage in the work that we do. And I think that we are the wall between the normal folks and the people that use their power to spread fear and hate, especially in times like these. So I'm going to ask you. Y'all the movers and the shakers, you know, the thought leaders: What are you gonna do with the gifts that you've been given to break us from the fear the binds us every day? Because, see, I'm afraid every day. I can't remember a time when I wasn't. But once I figured out that fear was not put in me to cripple me, it was there to protect me, and once I figured out how to use that fear, I found my power. Thank you. (Applause)
La policía, ante una comunidad en luto, respondió con el uso de la fuerza para infundir miedo: a una fuerza militarizada, al encarcelamiento, a las multas. La prensa incluso trató de provocar que nos temiéramos unos a otros por la forma de presentar la historia. Y este tipo de cosas ya había resultado antes. Pero como dije, esta vez fue diferente. La muerte de Michael Brown y la forma en que trataron a la comunidad desató una ola de protestas en Ferguson, St. Louis y en sus alrededores. Cuando salí a esas protestas cerca del cuarto o quinto día, no fue por valentía. Fue por culpa. Como ven, soy negro. No sé si lo notaron. (Risas) Pero no podía quedarme en St. Louis, a solo unos minutos de Ferguson, y no ir a ver. Así que decidí ir a echarle un vistazo. Cundo llegué allá, encontré algo sorprendente. Percibí enojo, mucho enojo. Pero lo que más encontré fue amor. Personas con amor a sí mismos. Amor por su comunidad. Y fue hermoso, hasta que llegó la policía. Entones intervino una nueva emoción en la conversación: el miedo. Ahora, no voy a mentir, cuando vi los vehículos blindados, y todo ese equipo, y todas esas armas, y todos esos efectivos, estaba aterrado, en lo personal. Y cuando miré a la multitud, vi a muchas personas a las que les sucedía lo mismo. Pero también vi gente que tenía algo más en su interior. Y eso era valentía. Esas personas gritaban, y se desgañitaban, y no tenían intenciones de retroceder ante la policía. Estaban más allá de ese punto. Y entonces sentí que algo cambiaba en mí también, y comencé a gritar a voz en cuello y me di cuenta que todos a mi alrededor estaban haciendo lo mismo. Y fue una sensación única. Así que decidí que quería hacer algo más. Fui a mi casa y pensé, soy un artista, produzco material. Así que comencé a hacer cosas especialmente para la protesta, cosas que fueran armas en una guerra espiritual, cosas que le dieran una voz a la gente y que les dieran fortaleza para enfrentar el camino por recorrer. Hice un proyecto en el que tomé fotos de las manos de los manifestantes y las puse por todos los recubrimientos de los edificios y las tiendas en la comunidad. Mi meta era crear consciencia y levantar la moral. Y creo que por lo menos por un momento, eso fue exactamente lo que hice. Luego pensé, quiero divulgar las historias de estas personas en las que veía tanta valentía en esos momentos. Y junto con mi amiga, cineasta y socia, Sabaah Folayan, eso fue exactamente lo que hicimos con nuestro documental "Whose Streets?" (¿De quién son las calles?) Me transformé en una especie de conductor de toda esa valentía que me fue dada. Y creo que esa es una parte de nuestra labor como artistas. Pienso que debemos comunicar valentía a través del trabajo que hacemos. Y pienso que somos el muro entre las personas normales y aquellos que usan su poder para difundir el miedo y el odio, especialmente en tiempos como estos. Así que les pregunto. A todos los activistas y agitadores, conocidos como líderes del pensamiento. ¿Qué van a hacer con los dones que se les han dado para liberarnos del miedo que nos ata cada día? Porque, ¿saben?, estoy atemorizado todos los días. No puedo recordar un momento en el que no haya sido así. Pero cuando me di cuenta de que ese miedo no estaba ahí para inmovilizarme, sino para protegerme, y cuando me di cuenta de cómo usar ese miedo, encontré mi poder. Gracias. (Aplausos)